okay Daniel I'm gonna let you or ask you
introduce yourself and just give you a
little quick summary about your history
and and then let you get started okay we
just change this view again there we go
right and well thank you everybody for
making time for this webinar and yeah
Who am I I have been well basically I
started off as a biologist and was
studying marine mammals and at some
point realized that if I continued to
study marine mammals my grandchildren
were probably only know of them from
picture books because they would go
extinct and so I decided to pay
attention to my own species but mainly
because I like marine mammals and and
that then took me to studying at Omaha
College doing a master's in holistic
science and later a PhD in design for
sustainability it was called design for
human and Planetary health a holistic
integral approach to complexity and
sustainability like a good PhD should
have a big chunky name and it was also
750 page thesis nobody wanted to read
and that was in 2006 and since then I've
been trying to explore what all that
thinking and all that research that I
did for my PhD and for my masters would
actually look like in practice so I've
spent some time working with the Eco
village movement lived at the Finland
eco village ramp in college to build
bridges between universities and eco
villages as applied field study sites
for applied sustainability and work with
pioneers brought Bioneers to Europe
and got invited to join the
international futures forum which is a
group of mainly at the time it was all
the consultants who'd already had their
career and really wanted to share the
tools of their career with the world and
they sort of realized that they needed
to bring in some fresh thinking and some
some younger ones and I was lucky enough
to be part of that and yeah so basically
in 2016 I published a book which I think
lying here yeah designing regenerative
cultures and since then I've started to
work with social media and putting my
writing online and not just my book but
also also the earlier writing and and
really that's in the work that has
created a visibility that that now
people are interested in having
conversations with me they could have
had them ten years earlier but
unfortunately I didn't share the
information so I'm really glad to have
this webinar because it's another
opportunity to share some thinking with
you and I would like to highlight from
the beginning from the start that I'm
I'm gonna talk for about four to five
minutes and really I would love your
feedback on this this is work in
progress this is not the gospel and you
don't need to believe it I'm just
talking about what I'm thinking about
this issue and then I would love to hear
your experience because I know that
Deanna has a link to the International
Society of System science and and so I'm
sure that some of the people on the call
will be more expert in all this than I
am
let me just try again whether I can do
this screen share properly should remind
everybody in those that joined be sure
and put in the chat where you're from
and any references you want to share
with us about your work and then any
questions you might have for Daniel you
can put in there as well
I'm trying to get rid of this little
window here I think your will not see
the window of all the people just on
mine okay good well let's get started um
I also have to say that because I this
morning I thought no I don't want to use
a presentation that I've used before and
so I've been building this presentation
mentally all day between taking care of
my 20 month old daughter and I haven't
quite finished so it's it's good enough
um so I'd like to start by repeating
that anything that is said is said by an
observers from Adana pointed out and
therefore every observation has a blind
spot but I also want to point out which
is what I learned from one of my mentors
at Omaha College Brian Goodwin that
really you can't be an observer you're
always a participant you're always
subjectively involved in the system
you're dealing with and really with the
title of moving into systems practice I
think that is at the core of what I'm
trying to explore today what it means
the handle has a Systems practitioner to
understand there are multiple ways of
knowing and they all can inform how we
participate in a system and that we
really are both the results of this
emerging complex dynamic system in which
we participate people with properties if
you all mute your mic then we won't have
the noise in the background but we also
basically all co-creative participants
of the system which means that
everything we do every day all the time
shapes the future of the world and for
me that is really crucial at this point
where
we are facing as gem Mandel calls it a
new term human extinction the
possibility that if we don't make more
appropriate choices about how to
participate in the biosphere as a
complex dynamic system that we might not
be around in the 24 22nd century or only
very few of us is is real and present
and we have young children going into
the streets and telling the world
leaders it's time to act upon this so
while a lot of what I will talk about
today might seem at a higher level of
kind of theory I think that's another
false dualism that we often work with
the dualism between theory and practice
the the meta design that the changes
worldviews and value system is really
the app stream end of the crisis that
that we face and so if you if you change
world gears and value systems you change
everything downstream and but but all
this theoretical framework that we'll
explore today is really in the context
of a very practical and urgent crisis on
the planet of how do we respond to
climate change how to respond to these
converging crises that were facing and
basically for me learning from Brian
Goodwin at Shu maha College the the key
insight that I got from Brian was that
science was now at a point where it was
understanding that we then we cannot
predict and control a system beyond the
very limited boundary of of a system and
that because we are always participants
the whole aim of science had to shift
from increased manipulation increased
control and prediction which is really
the agenda of the science scientific
activity since the Scientific Revolution
to understanding our role within this
complex dynamic system and how to
participate appropriate
and that in that is a shift from assigns
of that is mainly caring about
quantities and immeasurable to a science
of qualities that shouldn't fall
necessarily into the trap of trying to
measure quantity measure qualities
because the minute you you try to
quantify qualities you lose something
that is really important and so another
person who is very much linked with the
I Triple S and and the world of systems
thinking is Donella Meadows and in this
movement that way in of people wanting
to change the world for a better future
there's a lot of talk about paradigm
shifting and I really like pointing out
that there are two versions of Donella
Meadows famous article on leverage
points places to intervene with with the
system the first version I like to call
Donella Meadows 1.0 where she was still
very much that kind of modeling system
scientist trying to as long as we have
the right data and the right algorithms
we can create predictive models that can
inform us how to steer into a future and
then a few years later after realizing
the limitations of that in that first
version they were basically eleven
leverage points and they go down from
number twelve is the least important to
number one as the most important and in
the first paper she stopped with at the
level of paradigm shifts that's where we
have the highest leverage point and then
a later version of that same paper is
available that's where she added another
layer which is the the ability to
transcend paradigms the ability to not
frame everything in the frame of
paradigm shifts because what happened
when we do that we frame things in a
very dualistic kind of way we go from
this to that and to some extent it's in
the structure of language so to some
extent I will make will be making the
same mistake when I say that we need a
quality science of qualities I don't
mean that that means leaving behind a
science of quantities it just means that
the science of quantities is also only a
limited perspective and we need to
expand that perspective and give equal
value to understanding the qualitative
relationships in the system because
really ultimately the health wholeness
dynamism vitality of ourselves our
communities our bio regions and
ultimately the the the planetary
biosphere that the complexity we
participate in is really all about
qualities and qualitative relationships
and just because I was talking about
Donella Meadows also for those who
haven't seen this and there's a
wonderful paper that was initially
published in the whole earth review just
after Danella died quite quite early on
and they unfortunately far too early and
and this particular paper was later
turned into her latest book which is how
much you remember the title so sometimes
thinking insistence I believe and in
that she even gets more qualitative
about how we dance with systems it's it
really is like eating the metaphor it's
not leverage points it's not a
mechanical metaphor anymore it's it's
becoming a dance she's in the system by
saying it's a dance and and it's about
getting the beat and listening to the
wisdom of the system hitting multiple
perspectives in opening mental models to
criticism and feedback from others so we
can learn which is what I learned that
that I should have done with with a lot
of my writing ten years earlier I kind
of sat on it like an academic it wasn't
some kind of shell and some kind of
shelf in the university and because of
only one
put these ideas out can we have
conversations and their generative and
in these conversations we all bring
forth the worlds together asthma drama
and burial I like to put it and so I
really just wanted to drop this in for
for this kind of audience and assuming
that you're all sort of interested in
systems thinking that these three papers
are really worth taking another look at
and particularly the dancing word
systems one and another piece of work
that in this context I should mention is
Katya Laszlo's work where she says that
we really need to move beyond just
systems thinking to system's feeling and
systems being and which again says that
the same thing on the one hand says we
in the system were not externalized
observers and it begins to recognize
that there are other ways of knowing
that are important that are not just in
analytical analysis of theta because um
coming back terrific to so the crisis
were facing
like I haven't Baron who we're actually
don't know what just interact with him
on Facebook you recently put it
beautifully but by saying that um we're
now at a situation in in the world where
if we just look at the data if we like
like what we're facing is well we now
have to do like what Kevin said is we
now have to do the impossible because
the likely is unthinkable and I think
that's a powerful way of framing where
we are and if we just look at the
quantitative scientific data that comes
from the IPCC and and all the trigger
points in the climate system and and we
just look at the data of where we're at
with increased ideological separation in
the world with with the strongmen coming
back in in many countries with the the
evil monster fascism raising its its its
ugly head again
that we thought we long got beyond then
we could easily despair and say this is
this isn't going anywhere
so so really we have to almost trust
that there is something deeper that is
about a transformation of our entire
being and consciousness state that
because we're all part of the system and
co-creators of the system if we change
individually we actually in effect the
larger hole that that were part of and
if enough of us engage in that process
then we might just still have a chance
to to work that miracle that we now need
to work and and I love this wendell
berry very quote applying knowledge
scientific or otherwise is an art and
artist somebody who knows what to put
where and when to put it and I think
that's again that qualitative ability to
dance with system that I'm still
exploring and wondering how do I do this
work beyond just talking about it and
and intellectualizing about it and and
so again I normally don't put slides
with massive amounts of text but for
some reason like this group really made
me go back into quite an academic
presentation and but but I think it's
it's it's useful because I learned so
much from Brian Goodwin and and these
phrases really carry a lot and like the
the top one where he basically says that
to really understand how health and
wholeness emerges as as an emergent
property of this complex dynamic systems
at the different levels from cellular to
organ to individual to family to
community to by a redo to planet we we
need to look at the qualitative
relationships and we need to approach
things much more again from an aesthetic
feeling and an sensing and intuiting
into systems and not just from an
analytic thinking and I see this all the
time where we have
as long debates about masculine and
feminine and and and then lots of women
don't feel heard and it's and it's
partially because we still have this
strong cultural dogma that there's only
one way of approaching really factual
knowledge and it's the analytical
thinking male kind of way and I'm not
and I don't even like polarizing it
between male and female but is it's also
this that comes out with indigenous
cultures they they don't feel like bring
deep knowledge of living in place of a
million over thousands or even ten
thousand years into this conversation
which would be such crucial knowledge
that we have this ability to dismiss as
primitive knowledge we got excited about
scientific progress analogical programs
and I think it's all to do with buyers
of only valid dating one way knowing as
as human host these four ways of knowing
intuition feeling and thinking and
another person who's I think grappling
with exactly the same kind of issues
that again may be a reminder for people
to Mike because I hear people's health
phones and coffee cups and so yeah
another person to highlight and in this
context is Laura Bateson who I think
with this whole conversation that she
now started and the warm data labs that
she's running the conversation around
what is warm data she's really
addressing these same issues um you know
I'm kind of I can't really see my own
slides because of this well let me just
figure out how I get rid of this bar
because it's starting to irritate me and
no that's not what I wanted to do
and how do I get there ah okay great
so um yeah I guess the main point that I
wanted to make is Laura's is another
great source of people for people who
want to go deeper into this conversation
around how do we value new forms of
knowing or ancient forms of knowing and
how do we value different ways of being
an approach being in and approaching the
world and also the minute we we don't
pay that much attention to just the
intellectual analytical then we also can
give more value to multiple ways of
knowing and different perspectives
because really the complexity we're
facing is now so drastic that it's it's
impossible to have just one way of
knowing and to inform us about it and
I'm still stuck with this sorry about
this what's going on here anyway
I've got no know my screen is stuck okay
no sorry about this what is going on
basically I have
the screen where I see your faces down
to the show okay so right so yeah again
highlighting this this overall shift
into what does it mean to radically
accept participation as a notion that
gives us on the one hand an enormous
amount of responsibility because every
action that we engage in does affect the
whole system and does change the world
and I think it's a wonderful example to
look at this this 16 year old Swedish
girl greater turn Berg as an example of
that it is actually possible for one
individual to make a global impact and
it starts with a seemingly quixotic or
Don Quijote type action of thinking that
that by sitting in front of a parliament
and in Stockholm and this one little
girl could start a global movement and
she did and so it's it's I think we're
all called now to understand that we
have to become actors in this
last act of civilizational importance of
the end of in the of the era of Empires
in the beginning of the planetary era
and if we want to make this transition
from the era of empires from the era of
power over to the era of power with as
mature members of the community of life
again rather than an immature species
that thinks it can exploit the planetary
system it depends upon at infinitum then
we we really need to step from this not
just from ego to eco but really to step
into service and and ask this question
of what would it be like to participate
appropriately in the system and really
that's for me what designing
regenerative cultures is all about it
it's about how do we engage with our
communities in place and to make our
present a presence as human beings in
our local bio region or on the planet a
regenerative and healing one generative
and exploitative one and and so another
guidance system that that I found very
useful in understanding how we make
mistakes when we when we begin to think
in this way that we're all co-creating
this complex dynamic system wherein is
work from a German systems psychologist
called Dietrich Turner that was
summarized in the work of Finnish Fest
in 2004 and he basically what Dona did
is he here created a computer model that
was simulating what was happening to a
fictitious country and then a trend
transdisciplinary team of scientist was
a scientist was asked to basically run
the country and set certain
leverage points in the system and the
main point of this exercise wasn't
whether his computer model was perfect
but was to observe how these
transdisciplinary teams of scientists um
different like Economist's and and
biologists and very very diverse group
were interacting and responding to the
changes that they had decided and so you
can see that like the these main
mistakes that he pointed out are
basically the ones that we constantly
face when we look at getting things
wrong basically we define the the wrong
goals and we have not enough of a whole
systems analysis that really understands
nested whole logic systems and that
doesn't pay enough attention to
side-effects and then when we react we
oversteer and we which we try to rather
than dancing with the system we try to
force the system into into new ways of
doing things and one thing that I also
noticed in the work of my book is that
these kind of lists of common mistakes
or principles and they they're very
often they stay very intellectual and
very I tell you to if you list them in
this wave so what I fix explored in my
book in quite some detail is the power
of turning these principles and these
these guidelines into questions and
these are basically the same points that
Turner discovered and bother the last
one which I added but by turning them
into questions there's something
powerful that happens because if I tell
you a set of principles to follow
I'm basically telling you I've done the
work believe me I know what what needs
to be done just follow the principles
and all will be fine but if I turn it
into a set of questions then it becomes
an engagement then it becomes an
invitation to create collective
intelligence because I'm actually asking
the audience or asking the core
participants and what they think about
these questions and and it also means
that
everything becomes much more attuned to
the community and the place that the
question is asked in so it becomes play
specific and culture specific and for me
that that is like if I if I give you a
nutshell definition of what designing
regenerative cultures is all about for
me it's about co-creating elegant
solutions that are carefully adapted to
the bio cultural uniqueness of place and
this bio cultural uniqueness of place
that that we can't find solutions that
are global we can share best practice
and best processes we can share what
works in one place but we and and and
then explore in a questioning way
whether it might also be appropriate in
another place but we can't cut and paste
some solutions and in a similar way this
this economic knee-jerk response of how
do we scale it up might be inappropriate
because when solutions get scaled up
they often become problems rather than
solutions maybe it's about scaling out
and or reaching scale by spreading
meaning that these appropriate patterns
of participation happen at the local or
by a regional level in different ways
depending on the uniqueness of the local
ecosystem and the uniqueness of the
local culture and another reflection
years is that in the
title of designing regenerative cultures
is a paradox and it's to do with that
paradox of emergence and design that
really and cultures they they're not
designed they emerge they emerge through
the interactions and the relationships
through all those qualitative nuances
that that we tend to not pay enough
attention to in in a true quantity
focused science analytical science but
at the same time we do need to face the
future with some form of action and so
our intentions of how to participate and
the interactions and relationships we
create on the basis of these intentions
really do matter but it's this it's this
dance like for me that is really the
core of what I would like to have our
conversation or questions and answers
afterwards on is this how do we design
for positive emergence what what do you
do when you're on the one hand fully
embrace uncertainty and unpredictability
and uncontrollability of the systems
were in because you actually include
everybody and you include the the
complexity of not just trying to
leverage change with the usual suspects
that are already agreeing with you but
you're actually trying to work at the
bioregional scale with everybody in your
bio region in the context of the global
situation and so you you really have to
deal with the fact that there's lots of
people that see the world very
differently and for me that's an ongoing
inquiry how to do that well and as you
can see it's a blank slide which has
then finish it em another
of questions that that are basically
there were guidelines but I turned them
into questions then that might help in
this context is what my colleagues from
the IFF Graeme Lester and Maureen O'Hara
put together in a wonderful little book
which is called 10 things to do in a
conceptual emergency and and again all
of these questions point towards that
the same kind of qualitative issues and
the same issues that also Nora Bateson
addresses with warm data like these
looking at processes of change in
different timescales taking the long
view looking at how where the
intervention points are that that might
flip a system with a relatively small
intervention into a different state of
being and how to work with the system
when you're acknowledging that you can't
actually control it and did to some
extent all we can do is repattern the
present in order to bring forth a
different future together
and just to give you because all of this
is very abstract to some extent just to
to give you an example of how I've been
trying to do this in a very practical
way and just recently well it's not two
years ago that in my work with guy
education where I work as the head of
design and innovation helping to write
curriculums and create new courses and
new materials and when the SDGs first
came out in September 2015 the education
was already involved in the process of
drafting the SDGs as part of the UN
consulta Tory process because we were
part of an NGO that that is advising the
Economic and Social Council of the of
the United Nations and so when the SDGs
were finally endorsed by 168 98 nations
in September 2015 we set about creating
a course to help implement them at the
local level and I ended up with with
that the idea was to just create a
one-day workshop and I really used this
Buckminster Fuller quote of if you want
to teach people a new way of thinking
don't bother trying to teach them
instead give them a tool the use of
which will lead to a new way of thinking
as my my sort of guiding principle and
what I came up with is this idea of
these SDG flashcards that when they were
finished I I sold it like it was it was
really still the the better version that
that was sent to the two UNESCO our
partner in in the UN and they really
liked what they saw and and very quickly
before we even had enough time to
correct the what I would call the better
version these cards were then translated
into Spanish French Portuguese Arabic
Russians and Chinese and basically these
cards are structured in the same way
that all of Gaia education
curriculums as structured and we take a
four-dimensional approach to
sustainability so it's not just the
classic social economic and ecological
but it includes worldview as an
important fourth dimension and you could
call worldview culture you could call
worldview spirituality the bring sniff
brings up different responses in
different people but it's basically
acknowledging that this second-order
observation of how do I think about
things actually affects how I act in all
the other dimensions and is therefore
crucial and so each of these each of the
17s DG's is approached through three
cards which the cards actually help a
group process of living questions in
place about how are the SDG is relevant
to this place what is already happening
in this place that might help implement
this particular SDG and what could we do
to make it to co-create a relevant
implementation project about this SDG
and then also cross-referencing to other
SD G's in such a way that it guides
people into a much more systemic
understanding not just by thinking of
each of the seventeen from four
different dimensions but also thinking
about how how to link them all up and
create projects that that implement not
just one or two but but all 17 at once
ideally and so these cards come together
with a one day workshop process which is
called the training of multipliers and
and there's a there's a number of other
tools that that are used in that
workshop not just the cards one of them
is this idea that that I just used the
basic business model canvas that a lot
of people are probably familiar with and
I just tweaked the questions on the to
be specific to people working on
implementing a particular SDG project
and so that's the the SDG project canvas
and then I also created a handbook which
in a very detailed way
explains to people how to run this
one-day training of multipliers so the
idea here was not just to create a tool
that makes people think differently but
also to create an analog version of a
viral spread in a way and to basically
anybody who's done the workshop the
one-day workshop who has a set of these
cards and has a copy of the multipliers
handbook which which you can download
for free on the guy education website
could potentially if they have just the
basic skills of being a facilitator or a
teacher group leader could run the
workshop the next day in their community
or in their in their business or in the
local town hall and when in a school or
university to engage real people in
place around this idea of implementing
the SDGs and and what what I should also
say is that I'm quite critical of of
some aspects of the SDG process
particularly I think that the 169
targets under the 17 goals is where the
neoliberal Lobby has had a lot of
influence and has a yet again created
this bias because they're talking about
targets and measurements it's yet again
what an example of what I talked about
at the beginning of this talk and that
with to kuang quantity focused and we
missed the qualitative relationships and
and maybe in terms of the actual goals I
would say that the the goal that is
sabotaging all other goals to be
implemented is the way that cool number
eight is currently worded as decent work
in economic growth because it's it's not
addressing the underlying issue that
structure drives behavior in systems and
a system that has an inbuilt growth
imperative they because of our economic
system being based on a way of creating
money that creates money out of nothing
and when debt is created and then has
differential interest rates on loans and
deposits it therefore creates a need for
economies to have to grow at three
percent per annum or they collapse and
ultimately that is a driver
of degeneration and exploitation of
people and planet and if we don't
address that issue then I don't think we
will ever be able to implement all the
other calls and so yet again all of this
is an example both of an intervention
tool of how do we design for positive
emergence like you can see that all
these tools the cards the the canvas the
the book I can't predict and control and
manipulate much what these local groups
of people will come up with when they
have conversations using these tools but
I can create the tools that will enable
them and will guide them into a more
systemic way of thinking about the the
SDGs did the very tool itself might help
them to come up with ideas and and
projects that will actually result in
positive emergence rather than them more
of the same and so um how we're doing
for time because I on the one hand I
could go on but maybe I could also stop
here and and just on us some questions
and then we can go I think then I'd
rather than then going on much longer I
think I'd rather open up for
conversations and if I then feel like
picking up some more of the slide so I
can do that we just go here and stop
sharing I can see you all again
that's much better anybody online your
question just jump in here you just need
to unmute yourself or a reflection this
was too abstract yeah no I think it was
great you know when you were talking
about in economic growth I was thinking
about Rihanna's verse work
the caring economy you know she took the
GDP and then added all the social
indicators to that and like volunteerism
and things like that that makes strong
communities and strong Nations so yeah
we definitely need new indicators that I
mean GDP is goes up if you have a war or
if you have natural catastrophe and
so I can I can put in the chat box or
like I in my medium block that lots of
alternative indicators okay that was our
degree I I have a comment about
economics and it's really helpful to
hear what you have to say today Daniel
it really and my brains going mad at me
thank you for everything but that's a
system same isn't it and so in the
communities that were going to be
building in Bristol in England to start
with anyway we're using the
sustainability framework of one planet
living but we're also going to see what
we can do to put into practice
do not seek anomic like a trailer yeah
and so I'm in contacted her a fair bit
and my I put a slide in my presentation
about our project and so what she's
aiming to do is to meet everyone's needs
within the within the means of the
planet so that will that will become our
basic question our overarching kind of
question and we can keep asking each
other as we're building a medium living
it are all of the only thing left and
we've got some measurables from Kate now
and we can keep as well as having the
qualitative bit we can keep measuring
that within our little micro community
we're not overshooting the boundaries so
we're going to start playing with that
and then those other communities pop up
around the city and further afield see
if we can keep replicating that and as
you say each community is going to be
diff tending like paper
to see how things can be tweaked and
shifted and and by asking the same basic
questions and principles and how and
just not paying attention to GDP at all
focusing entirely on meeting everyone's
needs in our community and making sure
we're not overshooting and I'm hoping
that we can prove to one man Marvin
Reese who's still tied in to GDP but I
have talked to him about cake book I'm
hoping to prove that we need to look at
GDP at all so we'll see how we go with
that what I would say I mean what
wonderful initiative and and I love
Kate's work it's actually one of the
things that I really want to do more is
to include like bring Kate's worth and
work in my work closer together and
contextualize them and I mean from a
personal experience and I spent a long
time working with
the Eco village movement and also with
the transition town movement because I
was very keen on this and start local
think global act local and all that and
and trying to create patterns as back
back then in in 1999 when I tried to set
up an eco village in southern Spain our
aim was to be part of the solution
rather than to be part of the problem
but what I have got to in my own
learning is that we need to work at all
the scales at one in the same time like
what would you like because all the
models you're trying to build in a
renowned briscoe and are still sitting
within this nested whole urkki of
systems that are actually fundamentally
structurally dysfunctional and
degenerative and they will affect you
and and I mean at fintan we we try to
live a one planet footprint lifestyle
and and just after I got there
ecological footprint study of of the
community and it was half the UK but it
was by no means within planetary
boundaries so it's not that easy and to
create a system that that is within
planetary boundaries right now but
what's powerful about Kate's work is is
that she reminds us not to just look at
the ecological transgressions but also
the social foundations and the economic
foundations that enable people to do
that and but I but I guess for Ann what
I would encourage you to do is because
once you start a community process and
you really engage with it it's it's very
easy to create a bubble around that
process and and to only focus on that
and I think it understand these
initiatives in networks with other
initiatives that also happen in the
wider region around Bristol and even to
think of Bristol within its bio region
and to start really like I moved to
Majorca because I wanted to be in a
place where I could explore
transformative innovation by regional
scale how do we how do we work with
community but how do we do so in the bio
regional content it's like I think that
if we if we are to redesign the human
impact on earth in the time available to
avoid cataclysmic climate change we have
to come back to patterns that are more
by regional rather than national or only
local um because there's something about
that scale of multiple communities
working within a watershed to meet their
needs that you can actually get a
systemic whole systems design in place
to do what you're trying to do yes
because were looking at natural building
and one of the sites were looking at
house of woodland right next door with
lots of hazel copies that we can use to
start building with and but we're also
talking to people
you have a license to grow hemp in the
Bayeux region and starting to talk with
them if we could start to create some
kind of resource and local economy where
where we get all the materials we need
to build the houses in the city in the
bio region grow them locally and
encourage local landowners to do that
and that for me that when I say the
redesign is by a regional I think it's
also about creating a circular economy
at the bio regional scale that don't
make the mistake that the Ellen
MacArthur Foundation tends to make when
they talk about the two cycles of the
industrial metabolism biological
metabolism and they talk about it as if
astro metabolism cycle could go on
forever and but that they use this fancy
word upcycling and and and basically
it's physically and chemically
impossible and energetically impossible
to upcycle these kind of elements
continuously forever they what we really
need to do is to over the next 150 200
years contract that industrial
metabolism and and the biological
metabolism and in doing so that's the
process of climate change reversal
because we bring carbon back into the
soil will bring carbon back into
standing forests we bring carbon back
into the bio materials the houses
everything we use and in in doing so we
we not only build these regenerative
LaGrone biomaterials and local or
regional food economies which will give
people jobs and work on the social
foundations in terms of Akkad's work and
but we we also basically create a
response to climate change and so I
think that's that it's vital work it's
in its infancy we still have to a lot of
work to do maybe maybe we take a few
questions and then I answer them
is there anybody else who wants to ask a
question or comment sure I'd love to
jump in there Danny Hillis mark
Rowland's here actually it's my wife
that's names it up there loving your
conversations fantastic area that my
wife and I are focused on right now is
basically trying to energize the
movement within people and outside or
with organizations and governance so
looking at the schedule if you will and
being an engineer I tend to be very
pragmatic looking at the tightness of
the schedule I know you mentioned that's
a that's a very hopeful schedule of 12
years to make a difference and we're
gonna have to weather some serious
storms that we have to get moving as
fast as possible so I'm myself looking
at systems of governance and how we can
actually affect the changes and
movements within our governments that
are very caught in their own paradigms
at the moment still very much here in
Vancouver Canada very much a
capitalistic paradigm and everything
stems from that
so the trying to build hope in the
message joy in the messaging that we
have this incredible opportunity in the
human civilization where we have a lever
or a huge catalyst here for potential
global change towards the vision that
includes much of which is the global
goals the block being the lack of trust
and those borders in the stand and
they're not by by all regions they're
actually countries that are that with
with lines and limits based on cultures
and that are blocking much of this and a
lot of the power and control still
remains there and so you know when
you're seeing some of these incredible
movers I'm getting to my question some
of these incredible movements was with
systems thinking opera with theory you
and there's just so many more it's how
to pull these together into a real force
where we can start to move towards these
political systems and started I guess
encourage the Paul
additions to start seeing the world and
from a different paradigm to create that
very fast change you think do you think
that's possible to do that to get that
kind of movement and if not then how do
we move fast enough that's the big
question isn't it and do we want to take
a couple more questions or shall I
answer this one first people okay yes
yes not on that one in other parts of my
my writing if you if you go onto my
medium block and you just put in my name
and medium and then three horizons
you'll get a number of links to this
three horizon model that that is quite
useful to start thinking about these big
transitions that we need to make and um
the reason why I bring this up is
because they're the conventional sort of
that nation state and what is called
horizon one in this system that did
you're addressing is being still stuck
in the old paradigm one way of shifting
it is is to really pay more attention to
what's already growing some of the the
movements you've mentioned there's
there's a talk that I gave at fintan
that you can find on the internet on
human and Planetary health where I list
a lot of these movements around the
planet ecosystems restoration camps the
capital Institute's
regenerative communities Network and
their focus sites for where people
around the world have already committed
to creating bioregional regenerative
economies and trying to create whole
systems prototypes at that scale and and
I think that we need to combine all that
work rather than get too hung up in
arguing against each other about whether
it has to be regenerative or flourishing
or thriving all these different words
that we like to use to wreck
that were all part of these regenerative
cultures emerging as Paul Hawkens
reputedly put it it's the planets immune
response to the crisis that is speaking
through us as planet doing all this work
and and to really cherish the the
diversity and the the plurality of
approaches M almost like to see which
one works in because another thing to
keep in mind is that as we communicate
about this to people there is no one
language that will reach people equally
like if you look at the spiral dynamics
or the the integral model and people are
at different stages of personal
development and they will they will be
triggered by certain words like if I
talked to you about um she had the city
and participatory governance you will
resonate if I say that to somebody who's
in a different mindset they will
consider it as something challenging and
so that there's a wonderful article by
Barrett Brown called communicating
sustainability that he wrote in 2009 in
in cosmos journal and it's a great
example of of how we need to message our
message in different ways to different
people and it's not selling out like
it's it's just being skillful about
where you how do you begin you mentioned
trust how do you begin to build trust by
not alienating people from the start and
coming in with the vision that they're
not able to swallow yet but to take
people pick them up where they're at and
in many ways I think that the SDG are a
platform that allows that because their
systemic enough to address quite a lot
of the issues we do need to address but
they're the relatively conventional
platform that was built on a multi
sector multi-stakeholder process and and
then just briefly to how do we get to
scale I'm I'm constantly grappling with
that question and more and more
realizing that I've been talking in my
own echo chamber that the people that
I've got on the different Facebook
groups and in my Twitter feed and so on
all the people that I meet at
conferences were all in in the same echo
chamber um and we're talking to each
other about this and and yes the echo
chamber is growing what I like to call
the regeneration rising it's becoming a
bigger and bigger echo chamber but what
I think we really need to engage is all
the cultural creative mechanisms I think
we need to engage the musicians the
theater plays artists and fine art on
all scales that the big names and the
small neighborhood busker to basically
bring this way of thinking in this way
of seeing into the public and cultural
discourse in as diverse a way as
possible and I'm beginning to work with
a foundation on on these issues like how
do we create a traveling exhibition on
by biomimicry on regenerative
development and regenerative design and
in a way that engages some of the big
names in the art industry and through
them then brings people into this
conversation that that might just come
because each one of the exhibits also
has a painting by a famous artist and
but then they engage with the material
of the exhibit in a deeper way and and
you begin to build bridges to to those
other constituencies and similar way in
on the 10th of May I'm hoping to meet a
very famous might as well mention his
name Lenny Kravitz um somebody is trying
to put me together with Lenny Kravitz to
have a conversation how his work which
is already I don't know if you listen to
some of the lyrics from his latest album
raising vibrations I haven't listened to
some of his stuff for probably a decade
but but when I tuned in to that album I
realized that that it speaks the same
language as the regeneration rising it
speaks a language of one
for example is called it's enough and
another one is called here to love and
and they really do acupuncture with the
social system and address these issues
and and I think once we we engaged the
music industry and reach two or three
billion people on the planet at a very
shallow level if that's the funnel that
then brings only four or five percent of
them to the next level and then one
percent of those to a deeper level we
will already have a much different
situation as we have now we will have
created critical mass so so that's
that's why I'm putting my my work
towards important thing or described an
important aspect of getting our beliefs
out because we we're very passionate
about this then we know that we need to
do this but we have to find the right
language and the right avenues and the
right everything to actually interact
with people who don't quite get it and
and that's a that is a tap dance at
times to try to figure out what is the
right language absolutely and I and I
find it's people can also fall into the
trap of saying oh I can't mention this
to my client or I can't mention this to
the head of the City Planning Board
because they'll think I'm strange I
always find if if we find if you fight
the right if you find the right language
in the right entry points and you build
trust on a couple of issues and it is
okay to then naming that the larger
vision is a longer term vision and might
not be for tomorrow or the day after
tomorrow
but but it is important to also push the
boundaries and name these real
transformative changes and like like I I
think people have responded quite well
to some of the the means I've been
putting out which are these kind of
audacious statements like redesigning
the human impact on earth that's massive
um but I
I think that's ultimately what were
challenged to do but we're not going to
do it at a global scale from the start
it's it's this idea that you might have
heard this word glocal there's put into
the word together the word global and
local and I think that the
transformative action that is needed now
is local action it is working one at the
same time locally by originally in
globally and particularly like the
regenerative solutions are adapted to
the bio cultural uniqueness of place and
region the enabling factor is the global
collaboration and knowledge exchange and
I'd love to hear Johnny's take on like
because he's preparing this wonderful
conference in Malaga coming up very soon
on social innovation and how does this
all connect to what you're going to be
talking about room messy well the first
thing I would like to say is that
project 20 years ago that was called
local ecosystems so the local it sounds
very very connected to me and it's a
term that I've been using and in the
well my methodology that I'm sharing for
this 20 years is based on the concept
that we have to go to separate the
global bits like the immaterial world
has to go global but the material world
has to go local so is local is local
atoms and global bits so it has to we
have to differentiate these two aspects
of the economy and the reality what
things are in material what-what needs
we have that are in material and in the
ecovillage movement from where I come
from where I live in an eco village and
I'm part of the Eco village movement and
I'm head of economy in the movement in
in Spain we we believe that we have to
solve our our needs in our in material
needs in a completely different way as
we solve the material needs so we have
to go out of this materialism and and
focusing though in a more in different
ways of solving the economy so in SE and
was the question I wanted to to to pose
is we are planning to to create a vision
of the 2013 2030 have I like a good
vision that people can be inspired to
because we are talking about a lot of
catastrophic situation that we have
right now but I think people need hope
people need to see a place where we can
go and that's exactly what we are going
to do in Nessie we are going to try to
to create like an environment where
people can leave what the world could be
in 2030 in these six strands that we
divided NASA food and energy and Housing
and Finance and all these different
strands and we're going to try to work
to create the design create a plan to go
there but for me what I would like to
hear from you is how do you see a
realistic but ideal future in 2030 with
this with this way of thinking which I
completely share well I heard from
Thomas power the but you were blessed
trying to work with the three horizons
framework that I mentioned earlier and
in part of the strength of this 3d
rising framework is that none of the
three arises disappear so you have the
old system that also the red line still
exists on the far ends of whether the
third horizon has become dominant and
and that's a key message that we need to
also what is valuable about the current
system that we actually still want to
have integrate all 2050 I almost just to
push this time horizon out a little
further
like 2045 because 2030 is very close for
some real transformative changes to have
happened by then and and while I
completely understand that in order to
manage a large group of 600 or 700
people in different peril
screams music locusts and things like
that to some extent part of the the old
way of thinking to go food economy
housing transport and because somehow
they are also all related so if for for
process sake to manage the people you
want to start off with that theme um
fine
processes that also engage people to say
okay what are they what are the common
grounds and what are the intersection
points between these things how does
transport relate to economy ID how does
a housing relate to climate and or
whatever the things are I can't remember
the ones you mentioned but but basically
find a place to reintegrate that full
separation that that you created by
keeping it in the thematics and um and
the other thing that I find really
powerful about the three horizon
framework is that when you've done that
long journey of okay you've got the red
for horizon one has dips down and and it
becomes less prevalent you have the
green horizons three becoming more
prevalent and then you can use the
bridge which is really the social
innovation and innovation bridge of this
second horizon to avoid collapse and
rebuild and actually use that bridge to
get into a future without the trauma
that would come with a collapse and it's
a it's a powerful model partially
because when you get to the top of the
green hill of the third horizon being
prevalent and you look down at what
you're standing on you standing on red
ground and like you you're the new
horizons one and in that I think is a
powerful so I'm not gonna answer the
question of where do I where do I think
we're gonna be in 2030 M because I think
we're still gonna be on that journey and
it's a journey that will never end the
journey of creating regenerative
cultures is is a big because of this
dynamic understanding of process
and of our strange embeddedness in this
process that what you were saying that
the inner and the outer the material and
and and and the information are linked
and they inform each other they bring
forth each other and therefore this
process of inquiry will will go on
forever um and all we can do is is to
try to build the capacity of people in
place to keep responding to changes at
the local regional and global scale in
ways that increases the viability and
regenerative capacity of the system
overall um and and so really to because
also in response to the other question
earlier like we even if we get it right
in my opinion even if we get it right
and we do get to scale or skin like
there's enough of a demand like let's
say Friday's for futures and parents for
for futures get together and and builds
the political demand that political
leaders start responding in business
starts responding yeah um we're facing
this bizarre situation that
like 20 21 to 20 30 is the eCos the UN
decade for ecosystems restoration and
let's say we really put our effort
behind it and we pair this idea with a
climate change reversal response and we
pair this idea with donut economics and
we say we want to create the social
foundations and live within planetary
boundaries even if we did all that as
humanity for some reason we coordinated
our human family in that way we still
have to be honest about the fact that it
will be a lot of hard work and in the
next 10 15 years things might still get
worse even if in the next one or two
years we all decide to make the right
decisions and we all start working on it
full of full power and and I think for
our movement for the people that are
going to be getting rather than messy
it's really important to be clear that
because otherwise what we're gonna get
is this initial Wow Wow the regeneration
is rising and we're all doing it and
then after three four or five years
things are still getting worse in terms
of climate change effects and and global
floods and and catastrophes and then
people are saying it's not working
yeah the reality is that there's a
feedback like there's a delay in the
system that is why we took so bloody
long to respond 50 years we've been
knowing about that we needed to respond
to this and we're only just about
getting ready for it
you said glocal 20 years ago you started
the system yeah like em we need to be
honest that the next that three decades
I think are gonna be a really rough ride
and and we will see a lot of collapse
and we will see a lot of breakdown and
we need to celebrate that collapse in
that break down as the dissolution of
systems patterns and system structures
that no longer serve and and not be
fearful of the loss of terra firma and
and an institution's crumbling but we
also need to be really really clear that
that even if we get it right its way in
it for the long haul and and we never
really
neither there is no destination
sustainability and there is no
destination regenerative culture that is
perfect that we once we're there we can
duck down tools and live for help you
live happily ever after
it's it's a continuous journey sorry to
disappoint some things that aren't gonna
work so straightforward so so fast so
yeah it's important to have that in mind
yeah sure thank you thank you anybody
else and then you keeping time how we're
doing it's about 15 after so you got
about 15 minutes great
anybody else
Cummins yes here Daniel Hey Oh first
sorry sorry about my English but I will
I will try to do my best here all right
first first I have to thank you Daniel
because you have been an inspiration of
my my journey as a systems thinker and
practitioner as well so and basically a
person that is facing a transition from
the from the the story of separation to
the story of integration and therefore a
kind of brass being who we are
participants of this creative power of
the universe so and in this way I I was
you know I was working in business as
usual as a marketer about 50 50 years
and I started to to identification
disconnect between the being the same
and the doing of business organizations
so I start I started about 6 6 years ago
social endeavor
Hotels interactive is a systemic
consultancy that we are aiming to to
develop human organizations as reflexive
conversational and interdependent living
systems so in this way we are working in
what we call it the ecobee of
psychosocial capital L capital eco bio
psychosocial and you have been really
helpful in in in giving shape of this
build that is just starting it's just
emerging and he will I just want to say
it will be great to to be to be in touch
with you and keep on working of this in
this building and that's all that's more
than our question is I'm really grateful
for having this opportunity of
conversing with this collective mind we
are we certainly need to keep
reinforcing this view and I totally
agree and I'm really convinced that that
we need to start for the beginning and
education is it's important it's
important how we can change we can
cultivate new seeds of education because
education is the basis of all this
change we cannot do anything if we don't
intervene the education and that's my
main preoccupation I thank you hey thank
you for the feedback because it's always
like sometimes they one wonders why I
spent long nights putting stuff stuff up
on medium or posting things and so it's
always deeply appreciated to get
feedback like this that it actually was
meaningful to somebody and I I would
agree that education is is crucial in
all of this
like as I that definition of design
human intentionality expressed through
interactions and relationships so the
the most upstream intervention that we
can make is to change intentionality
because then so change the why we design
because then the how and the what we
design changes immediately once we
change the why and and that why change
happens through some form of Education
but education has unfortunately very
often been misunderstood is something
that you do in the first third of your
life and then you just work and then you
retire and and I think that the one of
the the great mentors of regenerative
development in in the Regenesis group
and one of the key principles of
regenerative development is local or
regional capacity-building
like building the capacity of people to
to live this dynamic process of adapting
and and so really education is a
lifelong learning process that that
needs to be at the core of what
regenerative cultures are really all
about and that that's why like when when
I first started writing my book it was
actually the working title I I started
the book under was called living the
questions together and this importance
of of questions and the importance of
engaging with other people around
questions because and that very process
is the process of building the capacity
of people to respond to change in a way
that is meaningful to their culture and
that is appropriate to the ecosystem
that they they live in um so in again
the the regenerative development work of
the Regenesis group and of Kara Sanford
they speak of three levels of work in
working regenerative lis and the first
level is personal development the
individual like it starts with the
individual and in our own work on
ourselves in our capacity to communicate
in our capacity to learn and be this
thing
Emily thinking patterns all of that and
so that's the work of the designer him
or herself then the next level of work
is is the design process and which I
would say is that engaging with others
in this process of living the question
this dynamic I'm not trying to find the
solutions and the answers but to
actually live the questions more deeply
it's this wonderful quote that I start
my book with by a Hyneman really look
away he writes in a letter to a young
poet you must live the questions more
deeply because you might not be able to
understand the answers yet and only if
you live the questions then maybe one
fine day will you live into the answers
and and for me so that's the second
level of work this process of inquiry of
how do we redesign the human presence on
earth but how do we do it in this place
out of this place in the context of its
culture and its history and then the the
the third level of work is what you
design and so that the processes and
structures and systems you put into
place and if they are designed
regenerative ly by people who work on
the first and the second level then they
should really increase the value and the
health and vitality of the systems that
they're touching and and that's where I
also see that my my previous work in my
PhD and and the work of the Regenesis
group and regenerative development is
very aligned because like I I work with
this notion of saluto genic or health
generating design and really when they
say increasing the value of the health
of the system to me that that's very
much the same issue like if if we only
asked ourselves one question with
everything we do in this kind of seventh
generation type way and does it increase
the health wholeness and vitality of the
local the regional and the global system
that's a powerful question to keep
asking about all decisions and
and if for some reason we feel it
doesn't then it might not be appropriate
participation okay it's the time for one
more but probably there's some parting
words you want to give us or well I'm
just always in encourage that people
actually make the time to engage with
the conversation like this and another
part of me is kind of glowing or there's
seven people that dropped out maybe they
didn't like what we talked about but
that's just to show that personally I
think they all had another engagement
but they want the recording yeah I'm
trying not to take it personal but just
to make transparent the personal
development process is ongoing as well
like I am I still kind of go oh maybe I
was too heady and all these these things
that don't really serve us to be like
one has to be self-critical but not self
[Music]
and yeah so so thank you all just for
for caring for for living into these
questions and for doing it in in your
community in whatever way you're doing
your work because it is all of us that
are going to make the difference and
that's what I'm absolutely convinced by
and um and that gives me a lot of hope
because it also means that we can be
more gentle with ourselves when we need
to just take care of our own needs and
and an energy sometimes because I like
the problem with with activists and and
and trying to work for a better world is
that it's it's easy to lose oneself in
burning out over that work and and I
always remember that like when I trained
in the way of counsel and one of the
core principles of the way of counsel is
that you always have to ask the question
which is actually a deep indigenous
wisdom ask the question
with anything you do does it serve
myself does it serve my community and
does it serve life or does it serve the
planet and as activists we'd find it
really easy to ask the question does it
serve my community and doesn't serve the
planet
but it's not so easy to ask the question
does it serve myself and in this new way
that I was kind of exploring in the
beginning if if everything is
interconnected and we're dealing with
this inter being state there's
fundamentally dynamic wholeness
transforming then the only way that we
can in a meaningful and continuous way
serve the health of the whole to come
forth is if we pay attention to our own
health and it there's nothing wrong with
asking does it serve myself because if
you don't serve yourself you're not
going to serve the community and the
planet for very long and so that's for
me maybe a parting gift or advice that I
also still have to remind myself of on a
regular basis and and when you look into
the screen and you see that there there
are sixteen people on the screen that
that cared enough about this issue to
make time for it then then you can also
take the time out to recharge and rest
because you know that there's other
people doing good work elsewhere and
then it's not you alone that has to do
it all so yeah six people that are vast
in and geographic areas like we're all
over the world too so that network is
just really dynamic so I just I want to
thank everybody for joining in today too
and and Daniel thank you for taking time
to do this it's been awesome it's been
an awesome presentation and awesome
discussion pleasure and and I I can
share the the PDF I don't know if you
have people's emails or something I have
everybody's email and I'll be I'll send
out the chat everybody for sure and a
link to the recording I'll send you a
PDF of the presentation and then you can
share it with people that'll be awesome
great thank you
thanks everyone thank you good luck
Johnny with messy
shame I can't be there Johnny thanks for
all the weeks the way yeah
many many links to check